<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Toy | Random code]]></title>
  <link href="http://jagg.github.io/blog/categories/toy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jagg.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-14T21:14:25+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jagg.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jose A. Garcia]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Encrypting Like It's 1553]]></title>
    <link href="http://jagg.github.io/blog/2016/09/03/encrypting-like-its-1553/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-03T16:46:54+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jagg.github.io/blog/2016/09/03/encrypting-like-its-1553</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The set up</h2>

<p>Italy, 1553, a book is published: La Cifra del Sig. Giovan Battista Bellaso. The book describes a
new cipher consisting on a table of character substitutions that, with the help of a previously
agreed key, could be used to encrypt a text.</p>

<p>This system is one of the simplest members of the family of polyalphabetic ciphers (the same family
as the Enigma machine) and has been reinvented many times over the centuries. At some point during
the 19th century it was misattributed to Blaise de Vigenère, a contemporary cryptographer who
invented a similar, stronger cipher. Thanks to this Bellaso&rsquo;s method is more commonly known as
the Vigenère cipher.</p>

<p>Even when this cipher wasn&rsquo;s as strong as the one really invented by Vigenère, it did quite well
for the next three centuries. During this time it was considered unbreakable until a method able to
decipher it was published in 1863.</p>

<h2>The problem</h2>

<p>Times have changed and we don&rsquo;t have to use a table to encrypt each character by hand in our
messages before sending them, we can just use a computer to do all the hard work for us.</p>

<p>The way to translate this cipher to our world of ones an zeros is quite simple. You choose a key of
size <code>n</code>, let&rsquo;s say &ldquo;KEY&rdquo;, and using its binary representation (e.g. ASCII) just apply XOR<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>
operations repeteadly between each group of <code>n</code> characters in our message and the key.</p>

<p>Decoding it it&rsquo;s just as easy. Literally just as easy, just apply the same XOR operations as
before over the cipher text and you get the original message!</p>

<p>Note that in the same way we can use computers to encrypt text easily following this cipher, they
can also be used to break it. The Vigenère can be broken easly if the difference between the size
of the encrypted text and the key is big.</p>

<h2>The code</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m currently learning Rust and this looks like an oportunity to play with it and see how it goes,
so let&rsquo;s see how we can model this in a more or less idiomatic way.</p>

<p>Our inputs and outputs are always going to be strings but internally we want to operate directly
with arrays of bytes. Also, we can leverage the type system a bit and create different types for
plain and encrypted text. With this in mind we can start with these structs:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub struct CipherText(Vec&lt;u8&gt;);
pub struct PlainText(Vec&lt;u8&gt;);
</code></pre>

<p>Also, chances are that once the plain text is encrypted it will not be valid UTF-8, so we need a
different representation for those bytes. Luckily we have all we need in the
<a href="https://github.com/rust-lang-nursery/rustc-serialize">rustc_serialize</a> crate, it comes with some
traits to encode and decode byte slices (&amp;[u8]) as Hexadecimal or Base64 (<code>ToHex</code>, <code>FromHex</code>,
<code>ToBase64</code> and <code>FromBase64</code>). Also, since our types are just wrappers on top of a Vec<u8> it seems
we could even derive these traits automatically, but this is not available in stable rust, so in
this case we can just implement some utility methods ourselves and make them return our own
custom Error type to make dealing with error conditions easier down the line.</p>

<p>So, we can implement <code>from</code> and <code>to</code> methods for our external representations (UTF-8, Hexadecimal
and Base64). You can see the Base64 methods for CipherText here:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">impl CipherText {
  pub fn from_b64(b64: &amp;str) -&gt; Result&lt;CipherText, Error&gt; {
    let cipher_bytes: Vec&lt;u8&gt; = try!(b64.from_base64()
        .map_err(|e| Error::Base64(e.to_string())));
    Ok(CipherText(cipher_bytes))
  }

  pub fn to_b64(&amp;self) -&gt; String {
    let &amp;CipherText(ref vec_bytes) = self;
    vec_bytes.to_base64(STANDARD)
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>We can also specify the different kind of errors we can deal with in our custom error type:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">#[derive(Debug)]
pub enum Error {
  Hex(String),
  Base64(String),
  UTF8(String),
}
</code></pre>

<p>Ok, now we can deal with our plain and cipher text without having to worry about in which format
they were, we just import them using the appropriate method and then we can forget about it!</p>

<p>So now we just need to do something with them, we want to be able to encrypt and decrypt text using
a key. As we said before both operations are identical for this cipher, we just apply a binary XOR
between the text and our key as many times as necessary to fit the full input<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<pre><code class="rust">fn repeating_xor(input: &amp;[u8], key: &amp;[u8]) -&gt; Vec&lt;u8&gt; {
    let mut out: Vec&lt;u8&gt; = Vec::with_capacity(input.len());
    unsafe {
        out.set_len(input.len());
    }
    for (i, in_val) in input.iter().enumerate() {
        out[i] = in_val ^ key[i % key.len()];
    }
    out
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now we have all the pieces, we can implement our encrypt and decrypt methods:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">pub fr encrypt(text: &amp;PlainText, key: &amp;str) -&gt; CipherText {
  let &amp;PlainText(ref bytes) = text;
  let xored: Vec&lt;u8&gt; = repeating_xor(bytes, key.as_bytes());
  CipherText::new(&amp;xored)
}

pub fn decrypt(cipher_text: &amp;CipherText, key: &amp;str) -&gt; Result&lt;PlainText, Error&gt; {
  let &amp;CipherText(ref bytes) = cipher_text;
  let xored: Vec&lt;u8&gt; = repeating_xor(bytes, key.as_bytes());
  Ok(PlainText::from_bytes(&amp;xored))
}
</code></pre>

<p>We should also write some tests to verify that our code actually works. We can take some text,
encrypt it and check if the text stays the same when we decrypt it:</p>

<pre><code class="rust">fn check_text(text: &amp;str) {
  let plain_text = PlainText::from_string(text);
  let key: &amp;str = "toy";
  let decoded_text = decrypt(&amp;encrypt(&amp;plain_text, key), key).unwrap();
  assert_eq!(text, decoded_text.to_utf8().unwrap());
}

#[test]
fn test_encrypt_and_decrypt() {
  check_text("This is the plain text\n");
  check_text("123, 456");
  check_text("!£$%^&amp;*@~:");
  check_text("日本語");
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Closing thoughts</h2>

<p>Now we have a very simple program that does something sort of useful, we can extend it to read and
write from files and create a simple command line interface to send secret messages in a completely
unsecure way!</p>

<p>The idea behind all this was to write some simple, self contained program in Rust to understand
how it works. In this case we haven&rsquo;t come across anything complicated, the ownership rules were
evident and we didn&rsquo;t have any lifetime issues so we&rsquo;ll have to pick something more complicated
next time to play with those things.</p>

<p>Also I haven&rsquo;t tried debugging, profiling or benchmarking yet, all critical things for any serious
production work so I still have plenty to investigate and maybe write about in my next post.</p>

<p>You can find the full source for this post in my <a href="https://github.com/jagg/vigenere">github account</a>.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This is really an XOR cipher, another substitution cipher with similar security. It&rsquo;s the same concept but it operates with bits instead of characters.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Note that if the key and the text have the same size we only have to do it once, that is called a One Time Pad and if our key was copletely random this cipher would be theoretically unbreakable!<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
